{
  "reference_number": "10523",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The target needs to be set in law now, being based on the best, most recent, climate science; it needs to ensure we meet our\n international obligations (Paris, 2015 Agreement); and be based on principles of equity. Cross party support is essential. All aspects of\n NZ society and its individuals need to be urged and supported to be pro-active in changing to a low carbon economy in secure and\n\n fast ways."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "And this needs to happen by 2040 to ensure a limit to global warming of 1.5d C. Total net emissions in our oceans and atmosphere\n so that we avoid ecological tipping points. CO2 at net zero by 2040 and immense and rapid reductions in other emissions, especialyy\n\n methane"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The main focus must be on rapidly reducing our GHGs, including those in the aviation and shipping industries. This option is the only\n way to ensure strong environmental safeguards. There should be NO RELIANCE, in any way, on unstable international emissions\n units."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only to increase climate action"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Altered only if it is to make greater reductions than stated/expected"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only if it means reducing emissions further"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The science of climate change must at all times be the key consideration - to refer to the ecology of the planet and its systems.\nOther considerations include equity, and Te Tiriti o Waitangi obligations"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely, if possible within 6 months"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Fairness / equity /health of the people and the planet; allowing for sustainable opportunities & technology relevant to a low carbon\neconomy; promoting a fair and just society founded on the principles of sustainability social, economic, cultural, environmental) and\n\nthus honouring Te Tiriti o Waitangi. All sectors of society must be included in this vital work"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It must set NZ's emissions budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "If it's to be an ETS. And the CCC needs to ensure NZ emits within (and hopefully under) its budget"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Climate science must always be at the front. Risk management, social impacts, obligations under Te Tiriti o Waitangi are vital"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Mitigation is a much, much more important role. The need is also for resilience in the face of uncertainties. I support its role in\nadapting to climate change, but bit's a less important role that dealing with mitigation"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We need a national climate risk assessment and a national policy plan as to how to address those risks. We also need a national\nclimate adaptation plan. Regular reviews of progress, at least yearly is needed in both areas."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As do all other people and nations, we need to learn rapidly how to live within the material and energy limits of our planet's\n\nenvironmental systems. This Bill, if courageous and bold, will improve the well-being of all New Zealanders and the land that supports\nus. Systemic changes are needed, and FAST - in our values, our priorities, our economy, ways of life. We need a radical shift away from\n\nexploitation of resources, and growth, towards nurturing the planet & the life it supports. radical shift towards a desire beyond all\nothers, to support and restore the life and our planet that makes living possible. That way, Papatuanuku and all life she supports, plus\n\nthe air around her will thrive."
    }
  ]
}
